Okay. בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
Today is the 24th day of עומר, Omer, it's three days. We
start today's דף Daf י"ט. Yud-Tes. We start at the bottom of,
well, we start at the bottom of י"ז Yud-Zayin עמוד ב', Amud
Bais, the משנה, Mishnah, the second to last משנה, Mishnah, the penultimate
משנה Mishnah there,
about five lines up, the lines get wide. We're still in the
question about צירוף, tziruf, but we will soon turn to a new
פרק perek which will move us into very central מעילה Meilah issues.
Let's first wrap up these issues about צירוף. tziruf. פיגול ונותר אין
מצטרפין. Pigul ve-nosar ein mitztarfin. So, if we had said that you
can combine all different types of פיגול pigul from all different קרבנות
korbanot and even different parts of a קרבן korban and similar by
נותר, nosar, but פיגול pigul and נותר nosar don't combine. If you
have a half a כזית kezayis of פיגול, pigul, half a כזית
kezayis of נותר, nosar, they're different prohibitions, so you don't get lashes
for either.
מפני שהן שני שמות, Mipnei shehein shnei sheimos, they're two different prohibitions.
השרץ והנבילה וכן הנבילה ובשר המת אין מצטרפין זה עם זה. Ha-sheretz
ve-ha-neveilah ve-chein ha-neveilah u-basar ha-meis ein mitztarfin zeh im zeh. Now, when
it comes also, we're back to טומאה, tumah, we had mentioned before
different types of צירוף tziruf of טומאה tumah like different שרצים, sheratzim,
but if they are fundamentally different טומאות tumos like a שרץ sheretz
and a dead rodent and a dead carcass of, let's say, a
cow or a dead carcass of a cow and the flesh of
a corpse,
אין מצטרפין זה עם זה, ein mitztarfin zeh im zeh, they don't
combine לטמא אפילו בקל שבשניהם letamei afilu be-kal shebishneihem even for the
lighter of the two, meaning as the משנה Mishnah before says, if
they have different שיעורים shiurim or they have different types of טומאה.
tumah. So, the נבילה neveilah and שרץ sheretz have different שיעורים, shiurim,
one is a כזית kezayis and one is a כעדשה. kedashah. A
נבילה neveilah and a מת meis have the same שיעור, shiur, they
both go by the size of a כזית, kezayis, an olive-size of
meat. Nevertheless, they're different טומאות, tumos, נבילה neveilah is an אב av
and a מת meis is an אבי אבות avi avot and has
seven days for touching and all these other implications, they don't combine.
And here, the repeating that point and saying they don't even combine
even like for the lighter of the two, meaning even if you
have a half of a כזית kezayis of נבילה neveilah and a
half of a כזית kezayis of a מת, meis, you don't say,
well, a מת meis is more strict than a נבילה, neveilah, let
it at least function like a נבילה. neveilah. And the answer is
no, they're fundamentally different categories, they don't combine. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל לא שנו אלא
טומאת הידיים מדרבנן. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel lo shanu ela tumas
hayadayim midrabbanan.
This is only when it's coming to the טומאה tumah of hands,
meaning the פיגול pigul and נותר nosar that don't combine. Now, there's
an issue about the prohibition of eating פיגול pigul and נותר, nosar,
okay, which it's also true they don't combine.
Excuse me,
that's what the גמרא Gemara is about to discuss. In terms of
פיגול pigul and נותר nosar don't combine for the prohibition of eating
פיגול, pigul, prohibition of eating נותר, nosar, the גמרא Gemara is about
to address the question of whether there is some
generic prohibition of eating that would combine פיגול pigul and נותר. nosar.
So we'll see that in a minute. So that's what שמואל Shmuel
is actually coming to say. He's saying that when the משנה Mishnah
talks about פיגול pigul and נותר nosar not combining, there's another הלכה
halachah of פיגול pigul and נותר. nosar. It's not just that they're
אסור assur to eat, but that they cause טומאה, tumah, they cause
impurity. Now that's rabbinic, okay. That's what it says, לא שנו אלא
טומאת הידיים, lo shanu ela tumas hayadayim, the טומאה tumah of hands,
which is rabbinic. Now the way you know it's rabbinic is that
it only causes טומאת ידיים. tumas yadayim. Any biblical טומאה, tumah, if
you touch it, your whole person, your whole body becomes טמא. tamei.
But rabbinically there are some טומאות tumos which if you touch them
your hands become טמא, tamei,
and פיגול pigול and נותר nosar are somewhat ironically, somewhat maybe sadly
not ironically,
the חז"ל Hazal were afraid that the כהנים Kohanim were crazy מחמיר
machmir and מקפיד makpid on טומאה. tumah. Okay, this was just a,
you know, an internalized type of a sociological reality that they were
crazy מחמיר machmir on טומאה, tumah, even more than things that were
forbidden to be eaten. If you just left פיגול pigul and נותר
nosar at the דאורייתא de-oraisa level and said don't eat פיגול, pigul,
don't eat נותר, nosar, they wouldn't care so much, big deal, it's
not going to affect my ability to bring קרבנות, korbanot, right? Basically
they're focusing on their role as
כהנים. Kohanim.
But you're ignoring it's חייב כרת. chayav kares.
Exactly. Well look, how about people nowadays that are crazy מחמיר machmir
on a lot of little technical חומרות chumrot but are very lenient
on a lot of fundamental ethical and moral בין אדם לחברו bein
adam le-chavero issues, you know? So people tend to have to, tend
to compartmentalize and often compartmentalization is about religious or ritual behavior versus
ethical, even though as we learn in פרשת קדושים, parshas kedoshim, you
know, there's plenty of ethical behavior which is religious and דאורייתא. de-oraisa.
Anyway, so כהנים Kohanim compartmentalized between things that related to the קרבנות
korbanot and things that didn't. So טומאה tumah for them was much
more stressed than the prohibitions of eating certain things, even כרת. kares.
So therefore חז"ל Hazal said, ah, the way we're going to do
it is we're going to say that פיגול pigul and נותר nosar
causes טומאת ידיים, tumas yadayim, and that way they'll keep their hands
off of it and they won't come to eat it. So apparently
they were so strict about it even for the דרבננס d'rabbanan's of
it, which is more, but of course as I said we know
today people are crazy מחמיר machmir for דרבננס d'rabbanan's of things as
long as they're more ritual and religious than they are for דאורייתאס
de-oraisas about like לא תשנא. lo sisno. So anyway, that was the
same here by the כהנים. Kohanim. So therefore when they combine, when
the משנה Mishnah says, excuse me, they don't combine, that's for this
rabbinic טומאה tumah of the hands. אבל מן האכילה מצטרפין. aval min
ha'achila mitztarfin. But
when it comes to eating they do combine, although normally for other
types of prohibitions we wouldn't say נבילה neveilah and דם dam combine
in other types of prohibitions combine. Here they do. דתניא, detanya, רבי
אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, לא יאכל כי קודש הם. lo yochal
ki kodesh heim. קודש בקודש פסול kodesh b'kodesh pasul בא הכתוב ליתן
לא תעשה
על אכילתו. ba hakasuv liten lo sa'aseh al achilaso. So essentially don't
eat them because they are holy, so this is from this we
learn a generic prohibition that anything that is invalid because of its
קדושה kedusha status, which as a classic examples is פיגול ונותר, pigul
v'nosar, are things that become פסול pasul because of their קדושה kedusha
status, that there is a negative prohibition. So there is a generic
prohibition, it's not כרת, kareis, but it's still true that they don't
combine to give you כרת, kareis, but they do combine for this
generic prohibition of לא יאכל כי קודש הם. lo yochal ki kodesh
heim. So he could have said לא שנו אלא לעניין כרת, lo
shanu ela l'inyan kareis, but anyway, he's saying that for this. But
you would get מלקות malkos for it?
But you would get מלקות malkos for it. So would you just
warn them or you'd just say you can't eat this,
don't eat this, this is an איסור issur of eating פסולי המוקדשין,
psulei hamukdashin, right. If you said this is an איסור issur of
eating פיגול, pigul, then that would probably... then that would not be
correct for פסול. pasul. Okay so now we look at the next
משנה. Mishnah.
Oh I see, so this... so this would mean that if by
accident we left over some meat for instance, yeah, it's got to
be burned. So the כהן kohen who picks it up and puts
it on the pile to be burned is going to have טומאה.
tumah.
Ah, yeah, even though
he's actually even doing a מצוה mitzvah or whatever.
I mean the
טומאה tumah is ידיים, yadayim,
it's not so hard to deal with, I mean you just dunk
them in a מקוה mikvah or whatever you've done with it.
You don't have to wait till
the night or anything, right? Yeah, correct.
Yeah, I don't know the הלכות halachos of... yeah, it's a good
point. Maybe they would do it at the end of the day
or I don't know how, you know, I don't know, that's a
good question how they would handle that.
It's a good question, yeah. Okay, let's take a look now at
the next משנה. Mishnah. האוכל שנטמא באב הטומאה... ha'ochel shenitma b'av hatumah...
thank you sir, by the way... ושנטמא בולד הטומאה מצטרפין זה עם
זה. v'shenitma b'velad hatumah mitztarfin zeh im zeh. Here is the case
where different levels combine because they're not the actual original source, they're
derivative. So let's say you have food that became טמא tamei with
an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, touched a נבילה. neveilah. This food is
a ראשון. rishon. Now let's say you only had a half of
a כביצה. kebeitzah. Food for טומאה tumah requires a full כביצה. kebeitzah.
And that also... there was another food that touched a ולד הטומאה.
velad hatumah. There was another food that touched I don't know a
person who touched a נבילה. neveilah. So that food... that food is
a שני. sheni. And you have a half of a כביצה kebeitzah
of each. מצטרפין זה עם זה לטמא בקל שבשניהם. mitztarfin zeh im
zeh l'tamei b'kal shebishneihem. They combine to cause טומאה tumah as the
weaker, obviously not the stronger. If you have half of a ראשון
rishon and half of a שני, sheni, you don't combine them together
a ראשון, rishon, but you could at least combine them together a
שני. sheni. So here it... seems to violate the previous rule, but
maybe yes, maybe no. Well, right. First of all, right, first of
all, on the one hand, it's the same שיעור, shiur, a כביצה,
kebeitzah, right.
And its טומאתן tumasun is not exactly שוה, shaveh, one is a
little bit more powerful, but at least the impact of their טומאה
tumah is the same, right, that it basically is טומאה tumah for
one day, you go to the... you know, you put it in
the מקוה mikvah and you're done. So it satisfies that criteria. But
more importantly, I think, is the point that Michael said, which is...
is that once it's not the original טומאה, tumah, it loses somewhat
of its identity. Right, this is just, you know, a ראשון לטומאה,
rishon l'tumah, a שני לטומאה. sheni l'tumah. It's like derivative טומאה. tumah.
It loses some of its character. And because it loses its character
it's much more genericized, abstracted right now. It's just derivative. It's not
the טומאה tumah itself. So this type of a case, you know,
what do you call... I'll give you an example. For example, there's
an איסור issur for a זב, zav, right, to enter into the...
to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, right. Okay, איסור issur for a
זב zav to enter. Now if a זב zav is a טבול
יום, tevul yom, so he has a little bit of the שיריים
shirayim of his original טומאה tumah but he's still a טבול יום.
tevul yom. There's actually a question that it also might be אסור
asur for him to enter into the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but
because still he's a זב zav with a weakened טומאה. tumah. But
if a זב zav touches me, right, or a... then that... then
I'm totally allowed to enter in. That's not... that has no quality
of it of טומאת זב tumas zav to it once it's derivative
טומאה. tumah. And that to me seems to be the basic point
here, which is that once it's derivative it's very generic. And since
it's generic, then at least they can combine for the weaker of
the two. They can't combine for the stronger of the two, but
they can combine for the weaker of the two. כל האוכלין מצטרפין
זה עם זה... kol ha'ochlin mitztarfin zeh im zeh...
so if a זב zav touches you, you're just טמא tamei until
the evening, but you
can still enter the בית המקדש?
Beis HaMikdash? Yes.
It's only the question about a... about a טבול יום tevul yom
of a זב. zav. But if it's a טומאה tumah that comes
through נגיעה negi'ah of a זב, zav, that's not טומאת זב, tumas
zav, right.
So טמאי מת tmei meis aren't supposed to be entering the בית
המקדש? Beis HaMikdash?
Well, I can't go into the... excuse me. Excuse me. I could
enter into the מחנה לויה. machaneh levayah. Excuse me, I could go
to הר הבית. Har HaBayis. I misspoke, right. The זב zav can't
go into הר הבית, Har HaBayis, right. No טמא tamei goes into
the מקדש, Mikdash, but if a טמא מת tmei meis can go
into הר הבית, Har HaBayis, a זב zav cannot go to הר
הבית, Har HaBayis, but somebody who touched a זב zav could go
to הר הבית. Har HaBayis. Yes, thank you. Yes, thank you, thank
you, I misspoke. Okay.
Okay. כל אלו מצטרפין זה עם זה לפסול את הגווייה כחצי פרס.
Kol elu mitztarfin zeh im zeh lifsol et hagiviyah k'chatzi pras.
Now rabbinically, this is another rabbinic טומאה tumah which we've spoken about
once before, which is that if you eat טמא tamei food, although
food cannot be מטמא metamei a person, right, a person can only
become טמא tamei through contact with an אב טומאה, av tumah, the
rabbis made a special גזירה gezeirah for various reasons we don't have
to worry about, that if you eat טמא tamei food and you
eat enough of it, you eat a half of a פרס, pras,
okay, right, a פרס pras is about what do you call it,
a פרס pras is about eight כזיתים, kezayisim, eight or nine כזיתים,
kezayisim, so you eat half of that, then you become טמא. tamei.
Now what size is that? How would that translate into a roll
of bread?
Four and a half כזיתים? kezayisim? I don't know. Depends what I
was eating last night. I was having some olives, I ate two
olives, and I was saying to myself, do I have to say
a, you know, an על העץ? al ha'eitz? Did I eat a
כזית? kezayis?
I'm not sure. That's the thought that went through my head. Anyway,
so if you really take a real כזית, kezayis, not the way
we go overboard about it, it's not a lot. What would be
four כזיתים? kezayisim? I don't know. Two slices of bread or something
like that. Anyway, okay, so you went ahead and you ate that.
Now, so, oh,
so let's say you had different foods. A little bit of an
apple, a little bit of bread, a little bit of this, they're
all טמא, tamei, they all combine to this half of a פרס
pras to make you
טמא. tamei. וכמזון שתי סעודות לעירוב. U'k'mazon shtei seudot l'eiruv. How about
if you have to do an עירוב חצרות, eiruv chatzeiros, which is
not the thing we do with the posts and the wire, that's
actually a צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, but what's needed in addition to
that is to make it like all the houses are united. So
we take a box of מצות matzos and we acquire it for
everybody who lives in that area, and now they're all combined within
the ownership of this food. But the food is food of שתי
סעודות. shtei seudos. So you can take all different types of foods,
and as long as they eat equivalent to the meal, two meals'
worth of food, that satisfies the עירוב eiruv requirements.
וכביצה לטמא טומאת אוכלין. U'k'beitzah l'tamei tumat ochlin. And in order to
be the size of a ביצה beitzah to cause טומאה tumah for
foodstuff, this is similar to the first point, but it would be,
maybe this is different, maybe this is talking about to initially receive
the טומאה. tumah. The first point was that they became טמא, tamei,
one became טמא tamei with this טומאה, tumah, one this, and you're
bringing them together. Here it's a lot of different types, not different
טומאות, tumos, but different foods are all combining to the requisite size.
וכגרוגרת להוצאת שבת. U'k'grogeret l'hotza'at Shabbos. The size of a גרוגרת, grogeret,
which is a, I always get this wrong, is it a pressed
date or a pressed fig? I think it's a pressed
fig.
ArtScroll says fig.
Fig, alright, I told you I would get it wrong. Anyway, for
the size of, it's because I don't eat figs or dates as
a regular part of my diet. Anyway, okay, but figs are the
ones that look sort of more like the round with the tip,
yeah, okay, fine. Anyway, okay, like a pressed fig for carrying on
שבת, Shabbos, that's the minimum size of carrying on שבת. Shabbos. וככותבת
ביום הכיפורים. U'k'khotevet b'Yom HaKippurim. And the size of a כותבת, khoteves,
that's the other one, that's the date, for יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
That's the amount that you have to eat on יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, fine, in order to transgress.
כל המשקין מצטרפין זה עם זה לפסול את הגווייה ברביעית. Kol hamashkin
mitztarfin zeh im zeh lifsol et hagiviyah b'revi'is. Similarly, if you have
different types of liquids that are טמא, tamei, then you drink them,
you yourself become טמא. tamei. That's rabbinic. If it's a רביעית revi'is
worth, which is like 3.2 ounces, so all different types of liquids
will combine for that, טמא tamei liquid. וכמלא לוגמיו ביום הכיפורים. U'k'melo
lugmav b'Yom HaKippurim. And there's by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the amount
you transgress is the amount that fills one cheek of liquid, and
all different types of liquid, a little orange juice, a little schnapps,
a little milk, whatever, they'll all combine. Okay, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. Very little גמרא Gemara on this. תניא. Tanya.
רבי שמעון אומר. Rabbi Shimon omer. מה טעם? Mah ta'am?
Why is it that a שני sheni will combine with a ראשון?
rishon? Food that is one degree derived will combine with two degrees
derived. שאפשר לשני שיהיה ראשון. She'efshar l'sheni sheyehei rishon. That it's possible
for a שני sheni to become a ראשון. rishon. Now,
so what does that mean? So let's take a look. The גמרא
Gemara doesn't understand what it means either. Now you could just mean
that the שני sheni could touch an אב av and become a
ראשון, rishon, which is maybe a way of saying that it's not
a source of טומאה, tumah, it's only receiving טומאה tumah and therefore,
but anyway, it's a little funny because what we're really trying to
say is that the ראשון rishon becomes a pseudo-שני. sheni. Since it
works like the more more like the lighter of the two, right,
it's not that the שני sheni becomes a pseudo-ראשון, rishon, but the
ראשון rishon becomes a pseudo-שני. sheni. But nevertheless, I would have interpreted
it to just mean that they're all somewhat generic here, they don't
have the character of the original טומאה. tumah. But let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. והגמרא אומרת. V'hag'mara omeret. ומי איכא שני דהוי
ראשון? U'mi ika sheni d'havai rishon? What do you mean a שני
sheni could become a ראשון? rishon? לאו אפשר. Lav efshar. It's not
possible, certainly not by itself. So let's see how the גמרא Gemara
reframes it. אמר רבא הכי קאמר. Amar Rava hachi ka'amar. מי גרם
לשני? Mi garam l'sheni? לאו ראשון? Lav rishon? Who caused, what brought
about the שני? sheni? Was it not the ראשון? rishon? about this
thing becoming a שני. sheni. Was it not a ראשון? rishon? And
because somehow it was a ראשון rishon that led to its status,
the ראשון rishon itself could certainly be combined for the שני, sheni,
which basically means that the שני sheni to some degree conceptually, but
wasn't necessarily this ראשון, rishon, but to some conceptual degree is a
derivative of a ראשון, rishon, or actually is, not just conceptually, derivative
of a ראשון. rishon. So the ראשון rishon itself, which is connected
to the שני sheni in the sense that it is, you know,
could have been the source of the שני, sheni, certainly works to
combine with the שני. sheni. Now again, this wouldn't work if it
were combining with an אב, av, like you couldn't combine a ראשון
rishon with an אב av and say, "Oh, well the ראשון rishon
became ראשון rishon because it touched the אב, av, so let the
אב av combine," right? Let's say you had, what would be an
example? I don't know, food touched a נבילה. neveilah. So then combine
a little bit of the נבילה neveilah with a little bit of
the food, right? But the point again is that this isn't the
source, both of these are derivatives and therefore more generic.
Okay, and why does it mean that אשר לשני שעשאו ראשון? asher
l'sheni she'asao rishon?
Yeah, they're they're reframing it.
They're just, whatever, they're not fitting it into the words, they're just
restating it in a different way. Okay, אמר רב אשי. Amar Rav
Ashi.
אמר רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi says: ראשון ושני לגבי שלישי בני
חדא בקתא אינון. rishon v'sheni legabi shelishi benei chada bikta inun.
ראשון rishon and שני sheni when it comes to what's the שני
sheni gonna try to be מטמא? metamei? It's gonna be מטמא metamei
likely תרומה, trumah, and תרומה trumah is a שלישי. shelishi. So from
the perspective of the שלישי, shelishi, a ראשון rishon and a שני
sheni are more or
less are like, you know, are all in the same category, all
in the same boat. They all have the power of being מטמא
metamei it, so it doesn't distinguish between ראשון rishon and שני, sheni,
which the רש"י Rashi מבאר meva'er says is not really a different
answer. It's really just another way of trying to say that these
are more or less in the same category and can combine, and
again, I would emphasize the point that I said, which is that
they are both, you know, derivative and generic, and therefore they don't
have the character of the original טומאה, tumah, and therefore they're able
to combine. בקתא? bikta?
It's like a group, what does the מפרש mefaresh say here? מבית
אחד הם, mibayit echad hem, they come from the same house. I
don't know if technically it means house, that's what he says. I
don't think it might mean like a valley.
How do they translate the בקתא?
bikta? Okay, anyway, yeah, the רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom also says
it means house.
House. Yeah, it's a way of saying same category. Okay, let's take
a look now top of י"ז ע"א. Yud Zayin Amud Aleph. הערלה
וכלאי הכרם מצטרפין זה עם זה. Ha'orlah v'kilay hakerem mitztarpin zeh im
zeh. Now ערלה orlah and כלאים kilayim combine with one another.
Now,
the one minute, excuse me. Okay,
so now, רבי שמעון אומר אין מצטרפין. Rabbi Shimon omer ein mitztarpin.
Rabbi Shimon says they do not combine. Now the question is, one
minute,
yeah, the question is,
so yeah, so רבינו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, I was just checking, רבינו
גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom explicitly says that it means to get lashes, which
is quite surprising because they are different לאוין. lavin.
So let's take a look at, let's first read the גמרא. Gemara.
The גמרא Gemara says: ומצטרף רבי שמעון לצירופי? u'mitztaref Rabbi Shimon l'tzirufei?
Since when does Rabbi Shimon need to say that anything combine? Yeah,
Rabbi Shimon says אין מצטרפין. ein mitztarpin. So the גמרא Gemara says
well, what does it even matter if they מצטרף mitztaref according to
Rabbi Shimon? והאמר רבי שמעון כל שהוא למלקות? v'ha'amar Rabbi Shimon kol
shehu l'malkot? Rabbi Shimon says that you don't even need a שיעור
shiur for מלקות, malkot, that מלקות malkot even is a כל שהוא,
kol shehu, so what's the even discussion? So the גמרא Gemara says:
תני אין צריכין לצרף. Tani ein tzrichin l'tzaref. So rather than say
אין מצטרפין, ein mitztarpin, he says it's not even relevant, they don't
even need to be מצטרף mitztaref because what do you call it,
because there's no שיעור shiur for מלקות. malkot. Now the real question
here is, what do you mean? You don't understand how they re-read
it?
No, but what is Rabbi Shimon saying, how are they re-reading it?
אין מצטרפין ein mitztarpin means I don't even need the צירוף. tziruf.
Because why? You're not gonna get מלקות malkot anyway?
No, you're always gonna get מלקות malkot no matter how little. But
you don't need to be מצטרף, mitztaref, you don't need to get
to a כזית. kezayit. Who cares? You don't need צירוף tziruf altogether
as a small amount you get מלקות. malkot.
So here he would give, okay,
double lashes because of a little of ערלה orlah and a little
of כלאים. kilayim. That's also true. Right. Now the real question here
is why, you know, why ערלה orlah and כלאי הכרם kilay hakerem
are מצטרף mitztaref since they are the same, since they are different
איסורים issurim and I have to admit that I did not, I
did not double-check, what, hold on one
second, let me get a chance to
check that out.
אור שמח Or Sameach has a comment says that the תוספות יום
טוב Tosafot Yom Tov citing a ירושלמי Yerushalmi explains that this is
the view of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who holds that all biblically
prohibited substances are accompanied by a single negative command and therefore they
all combine.
Right. Alright, so I, okay, I hear that. So yeah, the רש"ש
Rashash says what I would have said, which is that and he,
one minute,
right. And it's against what רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom said, but the,
but the רש"ש Rashash says that it's מצטרפין mitztarpin here means for
ביטול bitul purposes. That if you have a little bit of each
and they mix up with something that they prevent ביטול. bitul. You
know, that you don't say each thing separately. Now even
that is. do combine is itself a חידוש, chiddush, but ערלה Orlah
and כלאי הכרם Kilay HaKerem have similar שיעורים shiurim and in some
other ways of הלכות halachos of ביטול bittul they are combined, so
at least it's not such a חידוש, chiddush, but רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu
Gershom does go so far to say even for lashes and that
is a tremendous חידוש. chiddush. If you look at the מפרשים, mefarshim,
he also says a very, you know, hard to understand
line: ערלה וכלאי הכרם מצטרפין כדי להלקות עליהן בבת אחת. Orlah u'Kilay
HaKerem mitztarfin kedei lehakot aleihen bevat achat. But פיגול Piggul ונותר, v'Notar,
right, we'd actually said אין מצטרפין. ein mitztarfin. Although the גמרא Gemara
did say when it is מצטרף mitztaref איסור אכילה, issur achila, but
then it's not and then maybe that points to what Charlie was
saying. So I would check what the other commentaries on this, but
there definitely is, you know, some of a certainly a degree of
question about whether you can say normal צירוף tziruf here because the
normal rule is אין מצטרפין. ein mitztarfin. Let's take a look.
Yeah, Artscroll says that רמב"ם Rambam agrees that it's about ביטול. bittul.
Yeah, that's the פשט. pshat. The פשט pshat is again, versus רבינו
גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, that it's about ביטול. bittul. The question is about
what, you know, how רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom and the מפרשים mefarshim
are understanding it. Okay, so let's take a look now at the
next משנה. Mishnah. הבגד והשק, השק והעור, העור והמפץ, כולם מצטרפין זה
עם זה. Ha-beged v'ha-sak, ha-sak v'ha-or, ha-or v'ha-mapatz, kulam mitztarfin ze im
ze.
So we're back now to טומאה. tumah. The question is that there's
a minimum size of how big a material has to be to
be considered fit to become טמא. tamei. Okay, now if it is
a cloth, then it's measured by three fingerbreadths by three fingerbreadths, very
small. However, if it's a sackcloth, that's שק, sak, that's much larger
to be considered significant and become טמא. tamei. It has to be
ארבעה טפחים. arba'ah tefachim. Okay, so as opposed to like three inches,
roughly, it has to be ארבעה טפחים על ארבעה טפחים, arba'ah tefachim
al arba'ah tefachim, which is whatever that is, it's about a foot
by a foot. Okay, now a מפץ mapatz is a mat, you
know, like a woven mat out of, what do they make it
out of, some type of a reed or something. So that's even
bigger, that's חמישה טפחים chamishah tefachim by
חמישה טפחים, chamishah tefachim, sorry, ששה על ששה, shishah al shishah, excuse
me, let me just double check. No, I'm sorry, I skipped one.
Leather is חמישה על חמישה chamishah al chamishah טפחים tefachim and מפץ,
mapatz, a mat, is ששה על ששה shishah al shishah טפחים. tefachim.
All of those are how big you need for that material to
be considered significant material to become טמא. tamei. So now כולם מצטרפין
זה עם זה. kulam mitztarfin ze im ze. Okay, however, let's say
you make some type of a, I don't know, some type of
a patchwork thing with a little leather and a little cloth and
a little, you know, a little, what do you call it, a
little sack and a little of a little reed. Okay, so they
can all combine. Now of course they can't combine for the smaller
size, but they can all combine for the bigger size. So the
bigger size, let's say it's ששה על ששה, shishah al shishah, and
you have something that's mostly sackcloth or whatever, it doesn't matter mostly,
or mostly reeds, you know, a mat, and little patches of other
things, they combine to the size of a
מפץ. mapatz. Okay, אמר רבי שמעון מה טעם מפני שראויין לטמא במושב
Amar Rabbi Shimon mah taam mipnei sheru'in letamei bemoshov because, you know,
because they can all be, you can sort of, you know, sit
on all of them, they all, these different types of things, the
טומאה tumah for all of them, they all can share the טומאת
מושב, tumat moshav, which is when a זב zav or זבה zavah
sits on them, a זבה, zavah, right, or נידה, niddah, right, they
become טומאת מושב. tumat moshav. So therefore they're in somewhat, they're not
conceptually different things. Cloths are all talking about becoming the same type
of object for the purposes of טומאה. tumah. So therefore, again, one
that's more generic, they're not distinct types of טומאה, tumah, whatever, they're
all become a type of a cloth, a type of a מושב.
moshav. So one that's all generic, then they can combine for the
lighter, you know, for the more lenient of what they're being made
up of. Okay, which is similar to the idea before about food
and derivative טומאה. tumah. As long as it's generic, it can combine
as long as it's combining for the more lenient. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנא קטעה מכולן שלושה ועשה מהן בגד
למושב. Tana kata'ah mikulam shelosha ve'asa meihen beged lemoshov. Let's say you
cut strips out of all of them. Now it could mean you
cut strips out of all of them and combined them. The רמב"ם
Rambam actually reads this that you didn't combine them, but basic doesn't
really matter. The basic point here is is that when we talk
about if you have a little like patch of leather or sackcloth,
it has to be, you know, ארבעה על ארבעה arba'ah al arba'ah
טפחים tefachim or whatever, חמישה על חמישה, chamishah al chamishah, that's if
it's torn away from the original garment and was sort of like
it's leftover and it was by accident and it's just, you know,
leftover pieces. However, let's say you are intentionally, this is the way
the רמב"ם Rambam reads this, let's say you are intentionally trying to
make something that's a small size. Okay, you're cutting a little piece
square off because you want to make it a patch or you
want to do something specifically with that size. The fact that you
subjectively are trying to make something of this size and giving it
significance, then the thing, the objective size can be much less. Okay,
and that's the way רש"י, Rashi, so that's what it's about to
say.
Okay, so if you are specifically Specifically cutting it. So שלושה shlosha
three טפחים, tfachim, שלושה shlosha is טפחים, tfachim, שלוש shalosh is אצבעות.
etzbaot. The way Hebrew works is that the number is the opposite
gender of the thing that it's describing. Okay, it's very confusing when
you do טומאה tuma because ג' על ג' gimel al gimel very
often there's some, a lot of טומאות tumot that go by three
fingers and lots that go by three טפחים. tfachim. Okay, so you
always have to check. So שלושה טפחים, shlosha tfachim, הכי פירושו שלושה,
hachi peirusho shlosha, you consciously cut a piece out that was שלושה
טפחים shlosha tfachim by
שלושה טפחים. shlosha tfachim. ועשה מהם בגד ve-asa meihem beged and you
made out of them a cloth, so you know, a piece for
a garment, whatever. למשכב lemishkav if you're planning on using it for
something to lie on then שלושה shlosha three טפחים tfachim is enough.
Now maybe you're going to sit on it directly, you could probably
sit on something that's a foot by a... three טפחים tfachim by
שלושה טפחים shlosha tfachim is like what, nine inches by nine inches?
Still not, whatever, it depends, whatever. Okay anyway, but or you're using
it as a patch to patch over let's say a pillow. Anyway,
then it's שלושה טפחים. shlosha tfachim. למושב lemoshav if however, I'm sorry,
למשכב lemishkav is for something to lie on, excuse me, yeah, to
lie, exactly, a blanket or pillow. למושב lemoshav something to sit on
then that's even smaller, טפח. tefach. Okay, because obviously your blanket is
much bigger than a seat. לאחיזה la-achiza if it's just something to
use to hold things, כל שהוא kol shehu even the smallest size.
ואחיזה ve-achiza what does it mean to hold things? אמר ריש לקיש
אמר רבי ינאי שכן עומד לנבלא. amar reish lakish amar rabbi yanai
sheken omeid lenavla. You're standing now לנבלא lenavla you'd only think it
means to make it like disgusting, but anyway the מפרשים mefarshim תוספות
tosafot both say that it actually means
it comes
from, what word did they say it comes from?
Oh, I remember this, like in
גיטין. gittin. מטווה matve as a מטווה. matve.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, in גיטין gittin and הוריות, horayot, right, right, right,
from the word טבו tavu right which is to weave or to
sew or whatever. Anyway, they say that if you're working with the
strings on a, what's those things called? A loom? Right, so those
strings can be like, you know, they can be very sharp and
whatever, you know, cut you, whatever, they're very strong strings. So you
want like something, like a thimble. You basically want a thimble on
your finger, and therefore the smallest type of a thing would serve
as a thimble. Okay, so that's
לאחיזה. la-achiza. ומכניסה תנא הואיל וראוי לקוצצי תאנים. u-machnisa tana hoil ve-rauy
le-kotzetzei teinim. People that cut figs, so therefore yeah, you don't want
your hands to get all you know goopy, so therefore you can
wear these you know put these types of things on your fingers.
So there if you are cutting it, you're cutting it for, consciously,
then the sizes are a lot smaller and it goes and as
long as there's some reasonable use then it can become טמא. tamei.
הדרן עלך קדשי מזבח. hadran alach kodshei mizbeiach. So that is the
end of that פרק perek which was a nice little diversion from
יאוש, yeiush, all these questions about מצטרף. mitztareif. Now we turn to
this פרק perek and this פרק perek is of course it took
us only 18 or 17 דפים dafim to get to it, but
this פרק perek is the one where we are finally going to
get to the heart of the question of the act of מעילה.
meilah. Until now we've basically been talking about the objects right, what's
קדשי השם, kodshei hashem, קדשי קלים kodshei kalim at this stage, קדשי
קדשים kodshei kodashim at that stage, קדשים שמתו, kodashim she-meitu, קדשים שנפסלו.
kodashim she-nifselu. Fine, now we're finally going to talk about the act
and I've been telling you all along about thinking about these two
concepts as stealing and taking or deriving benefit. We are now going
to get into the heart of that discussion. Question?
Yes, I just want to make sure I understood this. So אחיזה
achiza is anything that's other than a משכב mishkav or a מושב?
moshav?
No, anything that's being used like this for a thimble to put
on your hand so that they don't... it's a type of a
thing to wrap...
So if someone used it as a band-aid it would be the
same idea?
Presumably right. Okay, let's take a look
now next משנה mishna next פרק. perek. הנהנה מן ההקדש שוה פרוטה.
ha-ne-ene min ha-hekdesh shaveh peruta. You derived benefit from הקדש hekdesh the
value of a פרוטה. peruta. There you go, the size, the amount
is
a פרוטה. peruta. doesn't matter, we said before קדשי מזבח, kodshei mizbeiach,
קדשי בדק הבית, kodshei bedek ha-bayit, they're all מצטרף. mitztareif. אף על
פי שלא פגם מעל. af al pi shelo pagam ma-al. Even though
it did not cause any damage into the original object right, then
you have been מועל. mo-el. דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei rabbi akiva. וחכמים
אומרים, va-chachamim omrim, the sages say, כל דבר שיש בו פגם, kol
davar she-yesh bo pegam, anything that has a damage, meaning that normally
when it's used the nature of the use is is that it
causes some wear and tear. Okay, so for example right? Like a
car. I was going to say the car example is a perfect
example, right? If you have to travel for business, right? You get
reimbursed not just for the cost of your gas but a certain
amount for the wear and tear on the car, right? There's an
assumption that there's you know that there's a certain cost. What?
If you get either... Oh really? Mileage includes the gas.
Okay so fine, the part of the חשבון cheshbon is the gas
and the wear and tear. Okay, so if it's something that has
some type of wear and tear, then לא מעל עד שיפגום, lo
ma-al ad she-yifgom, then there's no מעילה meilah until you actually have
some of that impact, some of that damage occur. ובשאין בו פגם,
u-ve-she-ein bo pegam, if there is if it's the type of thing
that there's no wear and tear,
כיון שנהנה מעל, keivan she-ne-ene ma-al, then as soon as there's מעילה.
meilah. So what the חכמים *Chachamim* are saying, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
is going to try to, you know, bridge the difference between רבי
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and the חכמים *Chachamim* and make it just on
a tiny point, but certainly the חכמים *Chachamim* here what they're saying
is that yes it seems to be fundamentally it's about נהנה neheneh
*nehene*, but if it's normally הנאה hana'ah *hana'a* comes in the process
of פגם pgam. *pegam*, then that פגם pgam *pegam* is also necessary.
We'll conceptualize that in a minute, but let's first finish reading the
משנה Mishna *Mishna*. Okay, כיצד *Keitzad*? נתנה קטלא בצוארה *Natna katla betzavara*,
let's say a woman took a gold necklace from הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*
and she put it and she wore it on her around her
neck. Okay, gold necklace?
Somebody
donated it, and they haven't gotten around to selling it yet. Okay,
טבעת בידו *Taba'at beyado*, or or a ring on her finger. שתה
בכוס של זהב *Shata bechos shel zahav*, or since we're in the
feminine because we were talking about the about the necklace, we're still
in the feminine, or she drank from a golden cup, כיון שנהנת
מעלה *Keivan shehenetat ma'ala*. As soon as you derive benefit you're מעל
ma'al *ma'al*, because these are things that there's you know, מעל *ma'al*,
I said מעל *ma'al*.
What? I said מעל *ma'al* instead of מעלה *ma'ala*.
Yeah, that's good, it should have been מעלה *ma'ala*, good point.
And כיון שנהנת *Keivan shehenetat*, yes. Anyway, all right. Anyway, these are
things that there's normally no damage to, right? There's no wear and
tear wearing a gold necklace or drinking from a golden cup. However,
לבש בחלוק *Lavash bechaluk*, now we're in the masculine again. Okay, if
if somebody is wearing a garment, okay, or כסה בטלית *Kissa betallit*,
or you know, a covering himself with a טלית tallit, *tallit*, and
as here doesn't mean like a טלית tallit *tallit* with ציצית *tzitzit*
on it, you know, it means a shawl, you know, some type
of an outer garment or whatever, something that would also be worn
on over the head, or בקע בקרדום *Bika bekardom*, or, you know,
chopped with a
hatchet, all these belonging to הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*, לא מעל עד שיפגום
*Lo ma'al ad sheyifgom*. All these things, even though you got a
פרוטה prutah, *peruta* of הנאה hana'ah. *hana'a*, if you did not cause
any wear and tear, then there is no מעילה meilah, *me'ila*, because
it require these are things that in their normal use there is
some lessening of the value of the thing itself. Okay, so those
are so these are just some clear examples of things in each
category. Finish reading it and then I'll talk about the sort of
what the implications are. הנהנה מן החטאת כשהיא חיה לא מעל עד
שיפגום *Hanehene min hachattat keshehi chaya lo ma'al ad sheyifgom*. If somebody
derives benefit from a חטאת *chattat* when it's alive, then there's no
מעילה me'ilah *me'ila* until it's פוגם pogem *pogem*. Now, we'll clarify this
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but for now let's just say that
the reason is, I mean the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* will make it
clearer exactly what exactly the point, but for now let's just say
that the reason is, is that normally when you use an animal
there's some, there's you know, like if you ride on an animal
or whatever there's a presumably there's some amount of wear and tear
on the animal itself, you know, not permanent necessarily, you feed it
and it can you know, whatever, if you get back its strength,
but presumably there's some amount, so you need to be פוגם pogem
*pogem*. However, כשהיא מתה *Keshehi meta*, once it's dead, כיון שנהנה מעל
*Keivan shenehene ma'al*, you're מעל *ma'al* as soon as you're נהנה neheneh
*nehene*. Now why? I mean it was dead and you use a
flesh of an animal there's also normally פגם pgam. *pegam*, but here
the real question to ask is why are you מעל *ma'al* when
it's dead? What about שמואל *Shmuel*'s statements about קדשים שמתו יצאו מידי
מעילה me'ilah *Kodashim shemetu yatze'u mi'yedei me'ila*, right? This is a classic
example of קדשים שמתו *Kodashim shemetu*. Ah, so Michael remembers or he
guessed or he both, that the very beginning of the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* read this quoted this משנה Mishna *Mishna*
of the מסכת *masechet* and said, ah, this would be because עולא
*Ulla* just says יצאו מידי מעילה me'ilah דבר תורה Torah *Yatze'u mi'yedei
me'ila devar torah*. This would be rabbinic מעילה me'ilah. *me'ila*. Okay, fine.
But as rabbinic מעילה me'ilah *me'ila*, so that number one solves that
problem. But also, fundamentally a dead קדשים *kodashim* has no use. So
if dead קדשים *kodashim* have no use, the concept of פגם pgam
*pegam*, right, is and this becomes an interesting question. Do you measure
פגם pgam *pegam* from the perspective of הקדש hekdesh. *hekdesh* or do
you measure פגם pgam *pegam* sort of in a generic sense? If
I normally were to be benefiting from a carcass of a dead
animal, that would normally be accompanied with פגם pgam *pegam*, so therefore
I need פגם pgam *pegam* here, that's one way you could make
the argument. What it seems to be assuming is no, is that
from הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*'s perspective, a dead קדשים *kodashim* is worthless. So
there's no concept of פגם pgam *pegam*. הקדש hekdesh *Hekdesh* is never
suffering as a result, you know, losing out anything as a result
of you being נהנה neheneh *nehene* from from a dead הקדש hekdesh,
*hekdesh*. So therefore, it's אין בו פגם pgam. *ein bo pegam* and
therefore you don't need to cause פגם pgam *pegam* and therefore as
soon as you're נהנה neheneh *nehene*. Any use is a problem. So
that's interesting, we'll discuss that more tomorrow when we get to the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* on that. But again, the conceptual point there is,
is that פגם pgam *pegam* is not measured necessarily by normally would
this type of usage of this type of an object accompany פגם
pgam? *pegam*, it seems at least from the end at least for
this rabbinic מעילה me'ilah. *me'ila*, question how much you can generalize it,
but it seems like the question is, does it cause a פגם
pgam *pegam* to הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*? Would it cause a פגם pgam.
*pegam* to הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*? And if the answer is no, then
you don't need that פגם pgam. *pegam*. Now, what is the reason
that you need the פגם pgam. *pegam* here? What's the logic behind
it? It certainly seems that conceptually the idea is about the הנאה
hana'ah *hana'a*. The idea is not about the פגם pgam *pegam*. The
fact that you're it's always about the הנאה hana'ah *hana'a*, sometimes based
on the case, it needs to be accompanied with פגם pgam *pegam*.
Now, let me actually just even ask you a question, which is
a good interesting way of testing this, how much when we measure
the שיעור *shiur*... How much do you have to be פוגם? pogem
Is it like I'm נהנה neheneh a פרוטה, prutah right, and I'm
פוגם pogem a כל שהוא? kol shehu? But what if I'm נהנה
neheneh a half of a פרוטה prutah? and פוגם pogem a half
of a פרוטה? prutah Do they combine? Do you have to be
נהנה neheneh a פרוטה prutah? and פוגם pogem a פרוטה? prutah So
the רמב"ם Rambam says you have to be נהנה nehene a פרוטה
prutah. and פוגם pogem a פרוטה. prutah The רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom
here in the מפרש mefaresh seems to say that you have to
be—that you can combine a half of a פרוטה prutah of הנאה
hana'ah and a half of a פרוטה prutah of פגם. pgam Okay?
I would have said—No, פגם pgam without הנאה. hana'ah No, that's clearly
not it. הנאה hana'ah is clearly the dominant theme here, we're going
to talk about that in גמרא. Gemara I would have said you
have to be נהנה nehene a פרוטה prutah and פוגם pogem a
כל שהוא. kol shehu. Right? That's I think what the משנה is
implying because I think that what it's sort of saying is is
that, you know, when look, there's a whole concept for example in
the גמרא Gemara in בבא קמא Bava Kamma about
זה נהנה וזה לא חסר, zeh neheneh vezeh lo chaser, right, deriving
benefit from somebody's thing and the other person didn't lose out of
it. Now that has limited applications, it's only קרקע, karka, not מטלטלין,
metaltelin, and so on, for various reasons. But nevertheless,
you know, there could be an idea that like if I got
some benefit off of your thing, let's say you have a light
and I come and I read by your light. Let's take that
example. You say, did I take something from you? I mean, it
was just there, you know, I took it from the air. I
took, you know, to what degree can you say I really took
it away from you? Now, of course, reading by a light of
a fire you lit is a little different than going over to
your necklace and putting it on and actually putting because I'm actually,
you know—but okay, but if we bracket גזילה gezeilah because גזילה gezeilah
is another form of מעילה, me'ilah here we're not dealing with the
גזילה gezeilah context, okay, because that's when I'm really trying to take
it away. Here I'm just borrowing it, just just wearing it, I'm
going to put it right back, okay? So still, obviously I'm more
active, but to the degree that I took something from you, I
took some הנאה hana'ah from you, right, if you didn't lose out
anything, maybe the argument can be made I really didn't take it
away in a particular sense. So maybe it depends. If it's the
type of thing where the whole הנאה hana'ah comes without any loss,
so yes, you're always—you are considered taking it away, that's what the
הנאה hana'ah. of this necklace is, it doesn't, you know, it's always
considered to be this this free הנאה hana'ah as it were, nothing
gets lost. But if the הנאה hana'ah is usually accompanied with some
wear, you know, some type of a wear and tear like for
the car or whatever and it happens to be that you got
the הנאה hana'ah. somehow magically in some special circumstance without that wear
and tear, then to some degree you didn't take it away from
me. I think that is the conceptually more of what's going on
here, that it's about defining it as taking away from הקדש hekdesh,
and in certain contexts to define it that way requires it be
accompanied with a certain amount of פגם. pgam Conceptualized that way at
the end of the day, it's not about, you know, it's still
about the idea about taking something from הקדש, hekdesh's but what you're
taking is not the object, what you're taking is the הנאה. hana'ah
So when we talk about it as—and this gets to again the
question about how do you generically under—how do you understand all the
different forms of הקדש. hekdesh? When you understand הקדש hekdesh as a
type of איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, is an איסור הנאה issur hana'ah
like עבודה זרה avodah zarah is an איסור הנאה? issur hana'ah? You
know, because it's הקדש hekdesh. you just can't derive benefit, then how
does it relate to the other הקדשות? hekdeshos? And how—where's the idea
of giving the money back? When we think about עבודה זרה avodah
zarah being an איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, you don't say if you
were נהנה nehene. a פרוטה prutah. from עבודה זרה avodah zarah you
have to pay somebody as a, you know, a פרוטה. perutah Right,
so here it's even we're talking about הנאה hana'ah it's not like
the הנאה hana'ah like the thing is taboo type of הנאה. hana'ah
It's still the הנאה hana'ah of taking something away from הקדש, hekdesh.
even if they don't lose out of it, but you took away
the הנאה hana'ah and you give it back and that certainly seems
like to be, you know, the way to be thinking about this
and in that way it would be similar to the מגזל migezel
type of it. So the פגם pegam. here is significant and we're
going to continue to explore this as we read the גמרא, Gemara
but let's take questions first.
How does missed opportunity for הקדש hekdesh? play into it? Let's say
you took the—How opportunity cost? Yeah, so you didn't damage the טלית,
but at the same time they were looking to use that טלית
at that same moment.
Right, or or the
כוס של זהב.
kos shel zahav. Right, but but oh I
see—oh you're saying your object's פגם pegam is—Is פגם pegam what if
what if the פגם pegam, is not in the object, what if
the פגם pegam. is in the opportunity cost?
The גמרא's Gemara about to say that you need the פגם to
be in the object. So it's a good point and especially if
you wanted to conceptualize it like I was trying to say you
took some—you took the הנאה hana'ah from them. If it comes at
a cost, that's taking the הנאה hana'ah and it wouldn't be so
object-focused. So, yeah, you make a good argument, but the גמרא's Gemara
going to say not. Whether that pushes you to a different way
of conceptualizing it, I don't know, but the גמרא's going to say
not.
Someone wanted to—I understand because even though the reference is in the
משנה to let's say the gold necklace or whatever is of things
that you misappropriate by taking, so would it be—But you're
not taking it to to possess it, it's not the גזילה gezeilah
type of—No, I understand, but you're
still touching it, you're using it, so, you know, would you say
then if I stepped in front of the fan of הקדש hekdesh
while it was on then and I'm נהנה nehene. because of, you
know, the cool air on a hot summer day, then I am
חייב מעילה?
chayav meilah? The only question there is that you're taking and
using. No, you
could be lying in it or whatever. Oh, you're just saying you're
physically benefiting from it. Well, the only thing is, as the גמרא
*Gemara* also says, כל המבריח אין בו משום מעילה me'ilah *kol mavriach
ein bo mishum meilah*, and shade is not really considered, but the
גמרא *Gemara* within that, within a discussion the גמרא פסחים *Gemara Psachim*,
it certainly considers the possibility that being in the being in the
shade of the בית המקדש beit hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash* could be a
what do you call it? Being in the shade of the hold
on, never mind, being in the shade of of the בית המקדש
*Beis HaMikdash* could be a form of מעילה me'ilah *meilah*. The גמרא
*Gemara* definitely considers that as a possibility. So in principle the answer
is yes, if that thing is considered a true act of הנאה
hana'ah *hana'ah*. That's the only question the גמרא *Gemara* has. Okay? So
in principle the answer is yes.
Are we going to discuss that here?
Some of that about what constitutes an act of הנאה hana'ah. *hana'ah*
is in that סוגיא *sugya* in in פסחים *Psachim*. So anyway, let's
take a look at the גמרא *Gemara*. Yes, ופגם *u-pegam* ופגם *u-pegam*
is like a a damage so to speak literally, right? Okay, but
it means here like some type of a loss. Doesn't have to
be a huge damage. So let's take a look at the גמרא
*Gemara*. תנו *Tanu*, we taught in a ברייתא braita *braisa*, מודה רבי
עקיבא לחכמים בדבר שיש בו פגם *Modeh Rabbi Akiva la-Chachamim bidvar she-yeish
bo pegam*, or we taught in our משנה *mishna* in I'm sorry,
no, ברייתא braita *braisa*, excuse me, בדבר שיש בו פגם *bidvar she-yeish
bo pegam*. Now in our משנה *mishna* it sounds like there's a
fundamental debate. That רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* just says אף על פי
שלא פגם *af al pi she-lo fagam*. It's all about הנאה hana'ah
*hana'ah*. But we have a ברייתא braita. *braisa* that basically says in
principle he agrees with the חכמים *Chachamim* that if it's something that
normally there is a פגם *pegam*, then it's only until you're פוגם
pogem *pogem*. So if that's true, במאי קמיפלגי *be-mai kamifligi*? So what's
their debating if they agree in principle that you need a פגם
*pegam* when it's it's a דבר שיש בו פגם *davar she-yeish bo
pegam*? So אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, בלבוש מציעא ומלמלא *be-levush metzi'ah u-milmalei*,
if it's a type of a middle garment or it's a type
of like a a thin type of a what do you call
it? A thin linen garment. Now, what does the middle garment is
it clear what that means? It means if your underwear, more, you
know, more easily wears out, right? Things that are outer garments exposed
to the elements more easily wears out. But things that are somehow
between your underwear and your outer garments, I don't know how often
people wear a third layer.
Don't you wear a shirt, sweater, and a shirt? A shirt and
a sweater.
A shirt and a sweater. If the shirt were totally protected, right,
but if it's a type of a thing that normally is is
totally protected from the elements and your body, then that doesn't wear
out so much. Now, what does it mean? I mean eventually it
still wears out. So you know, so the way the מפרשי *meforshei*
רש״י *Rashi* tries to explain it means that it's okay, but it
wears out like after a lot of time, you know, it's not
like there's an immediate loss at each, you know, each time it's
used. Certainly nothing that's discernable immediately.
And therefore that's the debate. Would you consider that יש בו פגם
*yeish bo pegam* or אין בו פגם *ein bo pegam*? How much
do you know, some meaning יש או אין בו פגם *yeish o
ein bo pegam* means normally is the loss accompany it? What if
it's very, very small and not immediately discernable?
That's what their whole debate is about because the ברייתא braisa *braisa*
basically makes them agree in principle, so as opposed to משנה *mishna*
that sounds that they debate in principle, now we have to make
it just a technical question of how do you define normally accompanied
with loss? Now, מלמלא *milmalei* or however you pronounce that, which is
a thin linen garment, if anything you would think that that's something
that is very easily damaged, right? But you know again, the מפרשי
*meforshei* פסבדו רש״י *Pseudo-Rashi* or whatever says that it means something that
is like because it's so delicate you only wear it very rarely.
And you only wear it very briefly. So if that's true, it's
not normally damaged I mean it can easily be damaged, but damage
doesn't normally accompany it because you only use it rarely. I guess
imagine like a very nice and beautiful silk scarf, right, and you
only took it out you only wore it very briefly and then
immediately you took it off and put it away, so you didn't
let it get damaged in its use. Which is again a little
strange because you would think that you would say
that doesn't matter how often you use it.
Well, it's in its normal use.
I know. So that's why the explanation
I hear I never wore my underwear they don't get damaged either.
Right, but in its normal use. I know. So that's why the
explanation I hear I
never wore I have
a hard time understanding that case. Let's move on, okay? We get
the basic point. תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*. Now we get to a
real nice direct addressing of the conceptual issues of what this act
of מעילה me'ilah *meilah* is. Okay? תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*. נפש *Nefesh*.
So it says נפש כי תמעול מעל timo ma'al *nefesh ki sim'ol
ma'al*, if a soul is מועל moel. *mo'eil*, which is going to
be the key question word of the מקדשי השם *mikdashei Hashem*. So
what's a נפש *nefesh*? אחד יחיד ואחד נשיא ואחד משיח *echad yachid
ve-echad nasi ve-echad mashiach*. Anybody, doesn't matter if you're a layperson, if
you're the king, or if you're the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*. Everybody.
Now probably it says that because there are different קרבנות *korbanos* sometimes
for a king, right, and you know for כהן משיח *Kohen Mashiach*.
אם הכהן המשיח יחטא לאשמת העם *im ha-Kohen ha-Mashiach yecheta le-ashmas ha-am*
and so on. אשר נשיא יחטא *asher nasi yecheta*. It's in the
context of that. So it's saying here those different statuses don't matter.
Everybody's the same. כי תמעול מעל *ki sim'ol ma'al*, when you do
an act when you transgress.
So what does this word מעל *ma'al* mean? אין מעל אלא שינוי
shinui *ein ma'al ela shinui*. מעל means to change. Let, I'll read
it and then I'll discuss it. וכן הוא אומר vechen hu omer
איש איש כי תשטה אשתו, ish ish ki tisteh ishto, any man
whose wife is סוטה sotah is strays ומעלה בו מעל uma'alah vo
ma'al and is מועל. moel Now again it's interesting what the standard
English explanation
is, is it betrays, transgresses? Does anybody know what the standard English
on that is? Trespass? No, מעל בו מעל ma'al bo ma'al in
both cases by the סוטה sotah is trespass. Trespass. Right. To do
something against is more often the sense, right, to go like there
are boundaries and therefore you impinge you right you violate in some
sense. But that's not how the גמרא is reading it. We'll talk
about what שינוי shinui means. Well, I'm going to talk, let me
read the next פסוק pasuk and then I'll talk about what this
means. ואומר ve'omer and it says וימעלו באלהי אבותיהם, vayimalu beilohei avoteihem,
they were מועל mo'el against the God of their fathers, ויזנו אחרי
הבעלים vayiznu acharei habalim and they fornicated after the בעל, ba'al, you
know, the idol, but specifically the בעל ba'al worship. Okay, now. So
what does מעל mean here? So תוספות Tosafot in its very nice
long תוספות Tosafot basically very nice conceptual one basically talks about two
types of מעילה me'ilah which are being reflected by these two examples
of סוטה sotah and עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. And he basically talks
as I've been telling you about the idea about הנאה hana'ah and
the idea of taking possession and גזילה. gezeilah. And he says that
basically there's one מעילה me'ilah? which is a sense of trespass or
שינוי shinui. that comes through pleasure essentially you know הנאה hana'ah which
is the act of adultery of the סוטה. sotah. Okay, so the
fact is that the husband and that's a sense of this adulterer
you know derived you know basically סוטה sotah here is being objectified
the woman you know but basically derives pleasure from this woman and
she was connected to her husband and that act of pleasure is
an act of שינוי. shinui Now שינוי shinui here would mean maybe
a good English word for שינוי shinui. that can change is divert.
It's sort of diverting this excuse me thing which is how it's
being treated here you know in the example from its proper you
know purpose, identity and so on. So this pleasure is deserved to
be for her husband and the fact that the pleasure was enjoyed
by this other man, that's a sense of that's one sense of
שינוי. shinui Okay. I'll just give the other example. That's one sense.
The other is the sense of not הנאה hana'ah but taking possession,
taking something away from him and he says that's the עבודה זרה
avodah zarah example. That these that rather than being as it were
connected to God, leaving God and going into the רשות reshut of
the עבודה זרה avodah zarah in the sense that now you know
because conceptually are you God's people or are you the idol's people?
Who's are you? To whom do you belong? And that's the type
of מעילה me'ilah? of trespass we would say of שינוי shinuy and
diverting which comes from being taken possessed by a different you know
outside being removed from the possession of one and put into the
possession of the other. Seth.
I'll take Rivka's place here. Please.
Well, I'm admitting that it's a problem, I said it was objectifying
the woman.
No, but precisely for that reason then why isn't the man punished,
why is the why is the woman punished? It's not the woman
punished?
Why isn't the adulterer punished? Well, the adulterer is punished but it's
the woman that has to be subjected to... right, so that's because
reflecting back...
you're talking about the pleasure, not the woman.
No, but conceptually if you if you do the translation of the
משל, mashal, right, the husband is הקדש, hekdesh, the woman is הקדש
object. No no no. The man, the adulterer is the one doing
the מעילה.
me'ilah No, the woman is taking something that belongs to the man
and giving it to someone
else.
Oh that well maybe
maybe yes and as well and the בני ישראל bnei yisrael are
referring their purpose to God the act
she would share she offered her husband she offered that act to
someone else.
Maybe. Maybe. And then it's the question of her getting pleasure. Yeah.
Right.
That's that's her pleasure.
Alright, alright, maybe. I mean that's an that's that can be an
active aspect rather than a passive aspect.
Right, I am yeah, okay, I get all that. To answer Seth's
question, I would just say, the point, the answer, like, so obviously
if they commit adultery and there's witnesses they're both punished. Why is
the woman subject to the מעילה me'ilah and not the man who
committed adultery is because in a patriarchal society she is under the
control of her husband and her husband basically can you know sort
of exert his rights and demand that she go under this in
the בית המקדש whereas a man you know even if he's married
in a polygamous society he is you know he is not limited
in the same way and nobody can exert their rights and force
him to undergo that.
No, I get all that but but the man is the one
taking the מעילה. me'ilah.
Right, and the woman is the one being subjected. But I think
they're both results of her being
more...
In your way of thinking that other model is different.
Alright okay.
Yes go ahead David. No I was just going to say why
are you saying if הנאה hana'ah if she's receiving הנאה hana'ah, then
isn't that an act?
But if she's objectified then I don't think that applies. Okay obviously
it's complicated.
Let me just see if תוספות Tosafot is clear about this. This
is a short תוספות?
Tosafot? No it's a long תוספות.
Tosafot.
Well
I will say so maybe I went a little overboard because I
will say that this תוספות Tosafot that sort of works the whole
thing out speaks by the סוטה Sotah he doesn't say that the
man was נהנה nehene that she was נהנית nehenit נהנית ועוברת. nehenit
ve'overet.
Okay so that fits better with the analogy.
I'm not so sure about that but okay. Because she is the
one being מועל mo'el? you're right because מעלה בו מעל. ma'ala bo
ma'al. Okay
yes okay I stand corrected that is the way she looked at
it he's looking at it. Okay so anyway okay good so she
so she's back to being the actor she's but at least she's
acting she's not being acted upon. Okay so fine but the anyway
one concept is again taking pleasure that is deserved for one and
you know diverting it. Okay and that's the שינוי diverting that pleasure
doesn't belong to that other man. Okay and the other is not
about the pleasure being diverted it's about the ownership being taken over
and worshipping עבודה זרה avodah zarah is not about some pleasure being
taken away but it's about taking yourself from God's control and putting
yourself into the control of the בעלים. be'alim. So those are the
two conceptual models.
They didn't have the man as
a alright alright I stand I said I think I let's keep
on going יכול גם בלא נהנה. yakhol gam belo nehene. Okay
those are the basic models. But let's says the גמרא maybe and
now the גמרא is going to clarify this this ברייתא it's really
a ברייתא right? The גמרא it's going to clarify this idea of
the need for פגם. Yes a ברייתא. Okay יכול פגם בלא נהנה
או נהנה בלא פגם. yakhol pgam belo nehene o nehene belo pgam.
Maybe it would even be מעילה me'ilah? if there was פגם without
הנאה. hana'ah. Maybe פגם itself would be enough. Or הנאה hana'ah? without
פגם? Right where we don't see any פגם in this case I
mean the husband's pride was פגום pagum but we don't see
a פגם. ובמחובר לקרקע uvemakhubar lekarka and why maybe there should be
מעילה me'ila even if something's attached to the ground? Again we don't
necessarily what if you were נהנה nehneh from a tree of הקדש?
Without פוגם you mean?
Regardless of that even with פוגם there's a הלכה halakhah that only
מעילה בהנאה me'ilah behana'ah doesn't apply to מחובר. makhubar. We're just talking
about how we know some of the other criteria. Okay. ובשליח שעשה
שליחותו uveshaliah she'asa shlikhuto now that's going to be an interesting case
which is going to be some משניות mishnayot but here's basically what
happens. If I go ahead and I tell James, James can you
go ahead and take that money over there and you know buy
something for me some apples for me from the store. Now James
thinks it's my money it really happens to be הקדש money. So
who is מועל? mo'el I'm מועל mo'el. not James. Even though מעילה
by the way is בשוגג beshogeg it's not because James isn't intentional
I actually also have to have made a mistake and been שוגג.
shogeg. If I'm intentional it's not מעילה but nevertheless there's a principle
by מעילה which would not apply by other cases that basically שליחות
shlikhut is relevant normally אין שליח לדבר עבירה ein shaliah lidvar aveirah
but here because it's on my behalf I am the מועל. How
do you know all these things are true by מעילה? James is
not. How do you know these things are true by מעילה? תלמוד
לומר בחטא talmud lomar bekhet here it says בחטא בשגגה מקדשי ה׳
bekhet bishgaga mikodeshei Hashem ונאמר חטא בתרומה venemar khet bitrumah and by
תרומה trumah it says that if somebody eats תרומה trumah unintentionally whatever
then it's ולא ישאו עליו חטא. velo yisu alav khet.
So we make a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. ונאמר חטא במעילה venemar
khet bime'ilah so it's a little redundant. מה חטא האמור בתרומה פוגם
ונהנה mah khet ha'amur bitrumah pogem venehene
by תרומה trumah when you eat תרומה trumah the תורה says you
have to pay it back with a חומש homesh so it talks
about eating תרומה. trumah. Well eating is a classic הנאה hana'ah, that
comes with a פגם. So that's going to be a model now.
Okay we're not going to limit it to eating but we're going
to use that as a model that it's הנאה hana'ah that comes
with a פגם. ומי שפגם
נהנה umi shepagam nehene the one who got the פגם who did
the פגם was also the one that was נהנה. nehneh Let's say
James is פוגם and I'm נהנה. That would not be מעילה it
would have to be the same person. ובדבר שפוגם בו נהנה uvedavar
shepogem bo nehene this is your point James which is the פגם
occurred in the same object. Let's say I was being נהנה from
one object of מעילה and being פוגם another. No it has to
be the same. The model is eating. Okay. ופגימתו והנאתו כאחד ufgimato
vahana'ato ke'ekhad
and they come at the same time. It's not like and this
gets to like the case maybe where the פגם comes לאחר זמן
le'akhar zman or something right it's not that the פגם comes now
and the הנאה hana'ah, later or vice versa they have to come
in the same. same act. Okay, so all of that tells you
the eating model tells you the idea of הנאה hana'ah coming through
פגם. ובתולש מן הקרקע u-ve-tolash min ha-karka and by תרומה, terumah, תרומה
terumah only exists after the stuff has been harvested. ובשליח שעשה שליחותו
u-vi-shliach she-asah shlichuto and there's a concept of שליחות shlichus by תרומה.
terumah. So we're going to learn that there's a concept of שליחות
shlichus by מעילה. Okay, that שליחות shlichus is going to come later,
but at least we're just putting it on the table now. Since
that's true by תרומה, terumah, אף תימר במעילה af teimar be-me'ilah פוגם
ונהנה pogem ve-nehneh you have מפגם mi-pegam ומשפגם נהנה, u-mishe-pagam nehneh,
the same person has to do it, ובדבר שפוגם בו נהנה u-ve-davar
she-pogem bo nehneh it has to be on the same object, ופגימתו
והנאתו כאחד u-pgimato ve-hana'ato ke-echad
the פגם has to come concomitant with the הנאה, hana'ah, ובתולש מן
הקרקע u-ve-tolash min ha-karka it has to be not connected, ובשליח שעשה
שליחותו u-vi-shliach she-asah shlichuto
and there's a concept of שליחות. shlichus. Now אין לי אלא אוכל
ונהנה. ein li ela ochel ve-nehneh. No questions, I want to get
closer to the end of the דף, daf, we only have three
minutes.
אין לי אלא אוכל ונהנה ein li ela ochel ve-nehneh take out
the word בדבר שאין בו פגם, bidvar she-ein bo pegam, that sort
of, that doesn't belong there. I only know the concept of your
eating and your deriving הנאה. hana'ah מניין אכילתו ואכילת חבירו הנאתו והנאת
חבירו הנאה ואכילת חבירו אכילתו והנאת חבירו שמצטרפין זה לזה אפילו זמן
מרובה? minayin achilato ve-achilat chavero, hana'ato ve-hana'at chavero, hana'ah ve-achilat chavero, achilato
ve-hana'at chavero she-mitztarfin zeh lizeh afilu zman merubbeh? Now how do you
know that you don't have to do it all? I can eat
a half of a פרוטה perutah and I can give Charlie a
half of a פרוטה perutah to eat, or I can eat a
half of a פרוטה perutah and I can put Charlie can put
oil be נהנה with half a פרוטה perutah or the reverse? That
it can actually combine around different people. Now it's a little bizarre.
Why isn't Charlie doing Charlie's מעילה? So again the point would be
I told Charlie to do it, maybe there's a שליחות shlichus idea.
There's a question does שליחות shlichus apply to הנאה? hana'ah, שליחות shlichus
might only apply if it's about more like גזילה. gezeilah. If it's
about הנאה, hana'ah then that more might be you know if it's
your הנאה hana'ah then you're the one that we focus on, not
me. So it might be that if it's talking about Charlie's
נהנה not as a שליח, shaliach, but I'm actually feeding Charlie, or
I'm putting it on Charlie. So I'm putting the oil on Charlie,
he's getting the הנאה, hana'ah but nevertheless I am still the one
if you would
conceptually taking the הנאה hana'ah from הקדש. I'm not necessarily the one
receiving the הנאה, but I'm the one taking the הנאה from הקדש.
So how do you know you can combine that? And eating is
really a form of הנאה, there's no status of eating per se.
So how do you know you can combine an eating and הנאה
and different people? That's just to read it. And even אפילו זמן
מרובה, afilu zman merubbeh, even over a long period of time. I
did it today and three hours later I did it with, I
put this thing on Charlie. תלמוד לומר תמעול מעל מכל מקום, talmud
lomar 'timo ma'al' mikol makom, regardless. Okay,
and we'll just read one final piece. אם החטא נאמר בתרומה לא
צירף שתי אכילות כאחת אף החטא נאמר במעילה לא צירף שתי אכילות
כאחת. im hacheit ne'emar bi-trumah lo tziraf shtei achilot ke-echat, af hacheit
ne'emar bi-me'ilah lo tziraf shtei achilot ke-echat. Let's say look, one minute.
By תרומה terumah you have to eat a כזית בכדי אכילת פרס.
kezayit bikhdei achilat pras. Classic אכילה achilah is you're doing it all
and you're doing it within a period of time. Maybe here, maybe
the זמן מרובה zman merubbeh isn't true? Maybe you have to do
it all within a certain period of time? מניין אכל היום ואכל
למחר ואפילו זמן מרובה? minayin akhal hayom ve-akhal lemachar ve-afilu zman merubbeh?
How do you know that if I ate a half of a
פרוטה perutah today and a half of a פרוטה perutah. tomorrow, even
after a lot of time?
תלמוד לומר תמעול מעל. talmud lomar 'timo ma'al'. Okay, so
therefore it says תמעול מעל even after a long period of time.
Just want to read one more sentence because it's the end of
the ברייתא anyway. מכל
מקום. mikol makom. אם החטא נאמר בתרומה פגימתו והנאתו כאחד. im hacheit
ne'emar bi-trumah pgimato ve-hana'ato ke-echad.
Anyway take, again that line seems to be wrong. מניין אכילתו ואכילת
חבירו ואפילו מכאן ועד שלש שנים? minayin achilato ve-achilat chavero ve-afilu mikan
ve-ad shalosh shanim? How do you know that? Okay now we have
the idea you and your friend combine. We have the idea you
when you do two acts it combines over a lot of time.
Let's take them both to an extreme. You did it today and
your friend did it a long time from now, אפילו afilu even
after three years from now. How do we know that you and
your friend's would combine even after a long period of time? תלמוד
לומר תמעול מעל מכל מקום, talmud lomar 'timo ma'al' mikol makom, regardless.
So what do we learn here? Besides learning the basic idea of
סוטה sotah עבודה זרה avodah zarah which are very nice at talking
about the different categories, we've also learned the idea from תרומה terumah
that at least when פגם is relevant, the הנאה comes through a
פגם, and we've discussed the significance of what it means to come
through a פגם. And at the end we've also learned this idea
that things can combine, הנאה and eating after over a long time,
even you and your friend. And the reason conceptually is because it's
not a מעשה אכילה. ma'aseh achilah. מעשה אכילה ma'aseh achilah is כזית
בכדי אכילת פרס. kezayit bikhdei achilat pras. It's anyway about a פרוטה.
perutah It's about taking something. And therefore at the end of the
day it's how much did you take away from הקדש? And therefore
it's taking away a פרוטה's worth from הקדש and therefore it combines,
it combines even over a long period of time and even if
it's me and Charlie. Now what makes it my taking and not
Charlie's? Either a concept of שליחות shlichus or maybe I put the
oil on Charlie, I feed Charlie and I put it right in
his mouth. But to some degree the point is I'm the one
taking it, I don't have to be the one benefiting from it.
I'm the one taking it. So this also very much points to
the
idea
that the idea of And just one last line, the
conceptually the line of
the גמרא said at the beginning, אין מעילה אלא שינוי, ein me'ila
ela shinoy, a sense of diverting something from its
purpose, like this belonged to הקדש, so הנאה or the ownership of
the object itself is being diverted away, that's important as conceptualizing again
what the idea of מעילה is.